[Music]
so these kinds of problems this is a
very very simplified version
of what are called in the statistics
literature as banded problem
s right so you know why they're called
Bandit
problems you know this
typic no oh come on you enough of lab
meetings to know these
things anyway so people know what a
one-arm bandit is
come on man anyway so one arm bandit is
a slot
machine you know what slot machines are
you put a coin there then you pull a
lever right and then what it
does it steals your money basically I me
all of that is mumbo jumbo you know of
course all of you must realize that no
casinos is going to put up a machine
that actually makes money for the
customer right so in the long run the
slot machine will steal your money right
and then you just keep pulling that
thing so that lever that you pull is
called the
arm right and since it has one lever is
called the one arm bandit because it
steals your money right so it's one arm
bandit so here this is very similar to
the slot machine except that instead of
having one arm it
has n arms right so each time you pull
an arm you get some kind of a payoff
right and if you want to really complete
the Bandit and ology so every time you
need to pull an arm you have to pay one
rupee right sometimes you get back one
rupee sometimes you get back nothing so
that way you know that it's certainly
stealing your money right so something
like that right so but that's
essentially why it is called a bandit
problem uh sometimes it it's also called
the multi-arm bandits right so it's
called multiarm Bandits because well it
has multiple arms right and the Dynamics
is very Sim SAR to a slot machine right
now we know why I kept calling actions
as
arms right so because the the the
literature typically talks about arms on
a bandit right but it's it's really for
us we don't have to worry about the
Bandit connections so then it's
essentially this
actions right good any questions so
far there are many many ways in which
you can solve this multiarm banded
problems right but uh the Crux here is
always that you have to be balancing the
exploration versus
exploitation right so I'll talk about
multiple
uh solution Concepts right what do we
mean when we say I want to solve a
multiarm banded
problem right so one solution concept
right
it's asymptotic correctness so what do I
mean by that I don't put any bounds on
you or anything right here is this
multi-arm banded problem so give me a
guarantee that eventually you'll be
selecting the arm which has the highest
payoff right as T tends to Infinity
you'll be selecting the arm that has the
highest payoff right so that is called
asymptotic correctness right so this is
one way of solving it a lot of the older
literature on Bandit problems
essentially concern themselves with
asymptotic correctness and then of
course they had some results on things
like rat of convergence and so on so
forth how quickly you reach the the
guarantee and so on so forth but by and
large the analysis was on asymptotic
correctness you come up with very simple
algorithms and then you show that the
ASM totically they will converge to the
right right right so this is the one
kind of thing right the second uh uh
popular
uh solution concept is essentially known
as regret
optimality suppose I
knew right suppose I knew from Time Zero
which is the best
arm right suppose I knew from the
beginning what is the best arm to pull
right and I keep pulling the arm over
and over and over again right and I keep
repeating this experiment multiple times
what will be my expected
payoff so this is
time expected payoff it's going to be
some kind of a flat line right so that's
possibly the best expected payoff that I
can
achieve right because I know from the
beginning I know what is the right arm
right but since I don't know this I have
to do this exploration right to figure
out which is the right
arm right so my payoff will look
something like
this right over time it'll eventually
reach that right as time becomes T goes
to Infinity I'll eventually reach that
point right so now
this reward that you see here right this
is what I could have got if I had known
the right answer from the
beginning right so this is in some sense
a loss that I incurred because of my
learning
process right so this is sometimes
colorfully referred to as regret so it's
like if I had known this from the
beginning you know I could have done so
much better so this is Regret so another
way of thinking about regret is that I'm
trying to maximize the total reward that
I obtain okay not just the
asymptotically the payoff right even
during the learning I need to get as
much payoff as
possible right so ideally I would want
this slope to
be pretty steep right if the slope is
very steep
so what will happen is this this this
area will come down right if the slope
is very steep this area is going to come
down but what is the tradeoff typically
you'll have to give up
is it'll take a longer time to reach
optimality usually there's a tradeoff
right because you typically to do this
right you will be giving up some amount
of
exploration right so there are some
Corner cases where you might actually
miss out on important exploration
because you are trying to be very
optimistic with respect to this regret
thing right so I wanted to
be I wanted to have very very little
regret so what what I might end up doing
is I might miss out on certain key
exploration that I should have done so
essentially what will happen is so in
some cases I will never reach optimality
also because I would have ignored
certain important outcomes along the way
so this is the trade-off that you have
to worry about but regret optimality is
essentially looking at how steeply you
learn at the outside okay of course that
doesn't mean I can be really bad right I
mean does it have a small
regret right but I did learn very fast I
actually went up the y-
Axis right but then I'm going to incur a
constant very very large constant regret
okay so that's not that's not so you
have to balance it right so because you
keep accumulating even though this has
reached here but you still keep
accumulating regret right so this is not
yet come to the optimal case in fact we
know that no algorithm can guarantee
that your regret will
grow small I mean essentially regret
will
fall right faster than Lo T so it has to
grow at least as Lo
T right suppose you have taken T time
steps the regret you have accumulated
till that point will be proportional to
log
T right so and as T becomes larger the
rate of growth will become smaller and
smaller right but that is the best rate
of growth that you can achieve all that
you can fiddle play around with is some
a * log T will be the rate right so that
a is what you can fiddle around with so
those constants you can fit around with
but log T itself is non-negotiable so
there are results that show that log T
is a lower Bond so you can't do better
than log T in achieving regret right so
essentially so if you think of this area
above this curve and between this dotted
line and this curve so that area will
keep growing at some rate
right as T becomes larger and larger
that area keeps growing at some rate so
the rate at which it will grow will be
at least Lo so that's the result that we
have so I'm not going to show you that
result but I'll we'll talk about a
couple of other uh other
things okay
so is it clear so people understand what
regret is
right good okay so third thing that I
want to talk about is what is
called pack
optimality right or not it's not I
shouldn't really call it pack optimality
but it should be more pack complexity
right so here's a little tricky
thing so pack stands
for
probably
approximately
correct
okay sometimes in a very loose fashion
we tend to use these as interchangeable
things yeah he probably right okay and
he's approximately right right so but
they are not interchangeable they very
different context very very different
things when they say somebody is
probably right that means he's either
right or
wrong okay so he's right with some
probability and he's wrong with some
probability right when they say
somebody's approximately
right he's almost surely not right right
but he very close to being right this is
essentially what approximately means so
it turns out that both of these concepts
are applicable in a bandit setting so
when I say somebody is approximately
right in the Bandit setting what do I
mean that I give you an arm right
finally you know what is the goal at the
end of the day I'm supposed to give you
an arm back right and and this is
supposed to have the highest expected
payoff when they say I'm approximately
right that means that arm I'm going to
return to you will be very close in
payoff to the the best possible
on right suppose I return some a to you
so Q star of a will be very close to say
qar of a star which is the best
arm right does it make sense so I'll
return some arm a to you at the end of
my algorithm Q star of a will be very
very close to qar of a star right what
is qar
again the true expected payoff which
which I don't know about right the
algorithm doesn't know what qar is but
it'll return an arm and the guarantee I
give you is the qar of the ter the
unknown Q star of the arm will be close
to the Q star of the best arm okay so
this is the approximately
correct okay so what is the probably
correct part
here
optim is the optimal no no no no it is
either approximately correct or not
because we already only gu giving you
approximately correct guarantees right
so with a very high probability it is
approximately
correct right with some small
probability it might give you an arm
that is more
than some distance away from the best
arm this is probably approximately
correct yeah that's what PC is probably
approximately correct oh okay probably
correct would mean yeah either optimal
or not optimal yeah probably
approximately correct is well with some
probability you are approximately
correct some probability you are not
right so typically uh there are many
ways in
which uh
people talk about this that a one one
popular way of specifying this is called
the Epsilon Delta pack uh where
[Music]
Epsilon refers to the the approximately
part and the Delta refers to the
probability part right so with the
probability of 1 minus Delta
okay the solution I return to you will
be within Epsilon of the best
arm right so this essentially
means probability that
probability that qar of a that's armor
return to you is greater
than
uh there's one way of writing it but
that is not what the pack framework
guarantees okay so what is the
difference between the first one and
this
one no that is the first one is relative
guarantee this an absolute guarantee
so you could think of either way you can
think of absolute guarantee or as a
relative guarantee but this is
essentially what pack op pack optimality
means right so for a given Epsilon Delta
if I can give that guarantee right then
you say that is back optimal for this
but what is the interesting part here
right if I allow you to draw an infinite
number of samples from the arms right I
can always guarantee this given give me
whatever Epsilon Delta I want I can just
keep drawing arms okay and then some
point I can say okay now I have
satisfied this okay the optimality part
comes in when you want to minimize the
sample
complexity right so given an Epsilon and
a Delta what is the smallest number of
times I have to select arms such that I
can give you that Epsilon Delta pack
guarantee right does it make sense so
that's essentially what we are looking
at here so this is a sample complexity
question right this is the correctness
question right this is a kind of a rate
of convergence question and this is a
sample complexity question so these are
all slightly different Notions of
solutions when I say you're solving a
banded problem these are different
Notions of solutions the kind of
algorithms that you come up with for
addressing each of these questions would
be pretty
different so how do you know qar a star
you don't know but I give you the
guarantee this is the if if you know qar
a star then this will be as close as
that so how will we know when when to
stop how will we know that will beep
what will
be number of exactly so these are
questions that we look at as we go along
I have not told you what the I'm just
telling you what the solution concepts
are right I not even told you how you
actually solve these problems right so
when we look at those I'll tell you how
to go about doing this in fact it'll
turn out that the algorithms themselves
are very simple okay but to analyze it
to show that this kind of guarantee
holds is where all the trick lies
[Music]
[Applause]